International Union of Physiological Sciences Records 1889-1989 Mss.610.6.In82
American Philosophical Society
- Series IV - Committees and Commissions
  The Congresses and/or the Executive/Council established various commissions or committees for specific purposes. While the commission or committee may report in due course to a congress or to the Executive/Council or both, some function in a time span greater than a congress or an Executive/Council meeting. Hence, this work was collected in a separate series whenever the commission or committee was seen to be established by the IUPS.
  Items relating to a committee or commission which appeared to be established by an Adhering Society or equal were filed together with the Adhering Society in Series II.
  - International Committee on Acoustics (Box 39)
  - Admissions Commission
  - Admission Committee
  - Scientific Committee on Antartic Research
  - Joint Commission on Applied Radioactivity
  - Commission on Auditory Physiology
  - Commission on Autonomic Nervous System
  - Committee on Biological Abstracting Abstracting Board, 1956-1971; 4 folders
  - Committee on Biological Abstracting Abstracting Board, n.d.
  - Commission on Bioengineering Applied to Physiology
  - Commission on Bioengineering in Physiology
  - Cardiovascular Commission
  - Commission on Cardiovascular Physiology
  - Commission on Cell Physiology
  - [Commission on] Cellular & Molecular Neuroscience [Report]
  - Commission on Chronoaiology [report Supplement], May 9, 1997
  - Commission on Clinical Physiology Electroencephalography
  - [International] Commission on Comparative Physiology, 1995-1996
  - Interunion Commission on Comparative Physiology
  - Commission on Domesticated Animals
  - Commission on Endocrinology
  - Commission on Environmental Physiology
  - Committee on Ethical Aspects of Physiological Experimentation - Commission on Experimental Biological Models
  - Commission on Exercise and Work
  - Commission on Fetal and Neonatal Physiology (Box 40)
  - Commission on Food and Water Uptake (Commission on Food and Fluid Uptake)
  - Commission for Gastrointestinal Physiology
  - General Committee
  - General File
  - Glossary Committee 1970 and After
  - Commission on Gravitational Physiology
  - Commission on Human Physiology
  - Commission on the Impact of Molecular Genetics on Physiology
  - Liaison Committee IUPS - IUBS - IUPHAR
  - Commission on Integrate Physiology
  - Commission on Medical Physiology
  - Membership Committee
  - International Commission for Microcirculation
  - Commission on Microcirculation
  - Commission on Molecular Genetics Applied to Physiology
  - Motor Control Commission
  - Muscle Commission
  - Commission on Muscle Physiology
  - Commission on Neuroendocrinology
  - Commission on Neurotransmitters and Modulators
  - Commission on Neurophysiology (Commission on Fundamental Neurophysiology)
  - Commission Neuro-Transmission
  - Nomenclature Committee Prior to 1970, 2 folders (Box 41)
  - Nominating Committee
  - Commission on Olfaction and Taste
  - Commission on Oralphysiology
  - Commission on Pathophysiology
  - Commission on the Physiology of Domesticated Animals
  - International Projects Committee
  - Commission on Psychophysiology
  - Ad Hoc Committee to Recommend Changes in Format and Conduct of IUPS Congresses
  - Commission on Renal Physiology (Renal Commission)
  - Commission on Respiratory Physiology
  - Committee to Review Commissions
  - Committee on Scientific Interchange (Box 42)
  - International Scientific Program Committee
  - Symposium Committee
  - Commission on Somatosensory Physiology (Somatosensory and Pain Commission)
  - Committee on Space Physiology and Research (COSPAR)
  - Commission on Teaching Physiology
  - Commission on Thermal Physiology, 1969-1990; 4 folders
  - Commission on Undersea Physiology
- Series V. Photographs
  In some instances, congresses were commemorated with photographs which in themselves are not the content of the congress or about the bureaucratic activity of the congress, such as the correspondence may be, but simply a visual record of the culture of the congress.
  Hence, photographs of all congresses have been collected under a separate series and are not included in the Congresses Series.
  Sometimes other meetings or individuals in the IUPS are also documented in photographs. Therefore, the Photographs Series is further divided into subseries.
  - Subseries A - Congress Photographs
    - IX Congress Croninger, 1913; 1 photograph (Box 43)
    - IX Congress Croninger, 1913 -; 3 Negative film strips
    - IX Congress Croningen International Committee, 1913 -
    - IX Congress Croningen Winkler, Hamburger, Einthoven, V. Rijnberk, Dekhuyzen, Zaardemaker, Magnus, Wertheim, Salmonson, V. Leersum, 1913 -
    - XII Congress Stockholm, 1926; 19 Photographs, 21 Negatives
    - XII Congress Stockholm Otto Loewi, 1926 -
    - XII Congress Stockholm, 1926; 19 Photographs
    - XII Congress Stockholm, 1926; 1 Photograph
    - XIII Congress Boston, 1929; 40 Photographs
    - XIV Congress Rome, 1923; 1 Photograph
    - XV Congress Leningrad, 1935; 3 Photographs
    - XVI Congress Zurich, 1938; 14 photographs
    - XVIII Congress Copenhagen, 1950; 3 photographs
    - XIX Congress Montreal, 1953; 1 Photograph
    - XX Congress Brussels, 1956; 12 Photographs
    - XXI Congress Buenos Aires, 1959; 3 Photographs
    - XXII Congress Leiden, 1962; 7 Photographs, 4 Transparencies
    - XXIII Congress Tokyo, 1965 -; 6 Photographs each (2 folders)
    - XXIII Congress Tokyo Photograph Album, sheets identifying persons in photographs, 1965 -
    - XXIII Congress Tokyo Photograph Album, 1965 -
      note: printed (at end of collection)
    - XXIV Congress Washington, D.C., 1968; 1 box
      Separate. (see Box 44)
    - XXV Congress Munich Delegates to General Assembly, 1971 -; 1 photograph each; 2 folders
    - XXV Congress Munich, 1971; 2 Photographs
    - XXV Congress Munich. R. Margaria, G. Kato, K. Kramer, U.S. Von Euler, 1971 -; 2 Photographs
    - XXV Congress Munich H. Drischel, 1971 -
    - XXV Congress Munich E. Neil, R. W. Hunsperger, P.O. Bishop, R. Thauer, H. Shaefer, R. Rahn, 1971 -; 2 Photographs
    - XXV Congress Munich Prof. A. R. Hodgken Cambridge, England and others, 1971 -
    - XXV Congress Munich Prof. Y. Katsuki, Prof. A. McIntyre and others, 1971 -
    - XXV Congress Munich Mrs. Hunsperger, Lady Eccles, Prof. R. W. Hunsperger, Sir John Eccles and others, 1971 -
    - XXV Congress Munich, 1971; 1 Photograph
    - XXV Congress Munich, 1971; 1 Photograph
    - XXV Congress Munich 1 Photograph, Sr. J. Eccles, Dr. Shaw, 1971 -
    - XXV Congress Munich, 1971; 1 Photograph
  - Subseries B - Other Photographs
    - Regional Congress - Brasov, Romania Prof. Wallace Fenn, 1970 -
    - Regional Congress - Brasov, Romania Prof. John C. Kendrew, 1970 -
    - Regional Congress - Brasov, Romania Opening Plenary Session, 1970 -
    - Regional Congress - Brasov, Romania, 1970; 2 Photographs
    - Regional Congress - Brasov, Romania Mrs. Zotterman, Prof. Y. Zotterman, Mrs. Benetato, 1970 -
    - Regional Congress - Brasov, Romania Prof. G. Benetato, Prof. Miron Niculescu, Prof. A. E. Asratian, Prof. E. Neil, 1970 -
    - Regional Congress - Brasov, Romania Opening Plenary Session, Prof. Wallace Fenn, 1970 -
    - Council of the IUPS in Oxford - Hertford College, 1968
    - Council of the IUPS Prague, July 1991
    - Council of the IUPS St. Petersburg, May 1995
    - Executive - Hungary Eric Neil, Mrs. Zotterman, Yngve, Zotterman, Kalman, Lissak, R. W. Hunsperger, Mrs. Neil, A. G. B. Kovach, 1972 -
    - Executive - Hungary K. Lissak, R. W. Hunsperger, Yngve, Zotterman, Eric Neil, 1972 -
    - Executive Meeting, Stockholm, 1972
    - First Committee on Biological Standardization of Drugs, 1923
    - IUPS Council Helsinki, 1989
    - IUPS Officers and Former Officers, 1980; 6 Photographs
    - Johansson, Prof. J. E.
    - Dr. Lundsgaard, 1967
    - Meeting of New Council - Munich, 1971
    - Outside the Dept. of Physiology - Karolinska Institutet - Stockholm, 1998?
    - The Permanent International Physiology Committee - Heidelberg, 1907
    - Photographs from Liljestrom -, 1927, (1929), 1951-1952; 24 Photographs
    - Photographs used w.: History of the IUPS, 3 Photographs
    - Physiological Society of Nigeria - IUPS workshop - Logos Nigeria, Feb. 1980; 3 Photographs
    - Second International Symposium on Motor Control (1980 Budapest), 13 Photographs
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1919 to 1990
    - XXIV Congress, Washington, D.C., 1968; 51 folders (Box 44)
- Series VI - History
  This series contains books, papers or statements which record collective histories or selective histories of the IUPS.
  - A Short History of the Physiological Society W. F. Brynum, 1926-1976 (Box 45)
  - A Short History of the International Congresses of Physiologists Annual of Science Volume 3 July 15, 1938 No.3, 1888-1938
  - International Congresses of Physiology 1889-1968 Fenn, 2 copies
  - One Hundred Years of Congresses of Physiology - Whitteridge, D., 1989
  - A Short History of the International Congresses of Physiologists - Franklin, K.J., D. M., M.R.C.P., [1938?]
  - Historical Demonstrations, 1976
  - Memories and Facts from Friends Here and Abroad - Wallace O. Fenn 1893-1971, [1975]
  - History of IUPS, 1968
  - Brief History of the I.U.P.S., n.d.
  - International Union of Physiological Sciences: Fenn
  - Subseries A - Constitution, By-Laws
    Contains background on the incorporation of the IUPS, its Constitution, By-Laws and Statutes.
    - Correspondence, 1974 (Box 46)
    - Application to Internal Revenue Service for Recognition of Exemption
    - Articles of Incorporation, 1969-1975
    - Certificates of Incorporation, 1969
    - Certificate of Incorporation, 1976
    - Constitution, n.d.
    - Constitution - Revised Copy for Incorporation, November 7, 1968
    - Constitution and By-Laws, 1986, 1989, 1993; 4 folders
    - Correspondence on Incorporation, 1963-1970
    - By-Laws Correspondence, 1958-1967
    - Fenn to Duyff Correspondence - Modification - Result of Legal Opinions, 1968
    - By-Laws Correspondence, 1992
    - By-Laws Proposed Amendments
    - By-Laws for Operation of the Council, 1956
    - Rules of Procedure, 1968
    - Statutes, 1953-1962
    - Statutes Correspondence, 1950-1969
- Series VII - Ephemera
  The congresses were also commemorated with medals, cultural programs, tours, and the like which, like the photographs, are not directly the content of the congress, but are part of the experience of attending a congress. Like the photographs, these materials and objects have been collected in their own series.
  - Certificate Issued to Wallace O. Fenn Designating Him Chairman and Delegate XXI Congress - Buenos Aires, 1959 (Box 47)
  - Discours de Monsieur Stenon - Copenhagen, 1950; folder - book
  - The Imperial Hotel, 1964; book
  - In Memoriam Wallace O. Fenn 1893-1971, 1979
  - Jaques Cartier et "La Grosse Maladie", book
  - Respiration Dinner, 1971; booklet
  - Some Dutch Contributions to the Development of Physiology, 1962; book
  - Some Founders of Physiology, 1956; black book
  - Some Founders of Physiology, 1956; white book
  - Strand-Hotel-Schlop-Berg, three autographed menus
  - The Way of the Investigator (Walter B. Cannon), 1968
  - Miscellaneous Cards, Maps, Brochures, Menus, 22 items (Box 48)
  - Miscellaneous Brochures, Cards, Maps, Tickets, Etc., 29 items
  - Newspapers, 17 items
  - Medals - Five Medals
- Series VIII - Bound Correspondence and Materials
  This series contains correspondence and other material that had been bound together (before the archives came to the American Philosophical Society) and such collected information that would have been otherwise filed under other series. Archivists at the APS decided not to disbind these volumes and file the documents into their proper places in the series described above, so it is therefore necessary to use the contents of these bound volumes in conjunction with related documents from other series.
  - First International Pharmacological Meeting - Stockholm, Sweden, Aug. 22-25, 1961 (Box 49)
  - Permanent International Committee of the Physiological Congress, 1935-1953
  - Second International Pharmacological Meeting - Prague, Czechoslovakia, Aug. 20-23, 1963